了结这段恩怨吧
See end to vengeance.
杀了葛雷博的老婆
Take the life of Glaber's woman
就像他杀了你老婆一样
as he took the life of yours.
孩子是你的
The child is yours!
你追求过民政官瓦里留斯
You sought Praetor Varinius' affections once.
你的话肯定能够打动他
Send message, and you could yet gain them.
你没有看到吗
Do you not see it?
诸神引导我一步步走近盖尤斯
The gods have led me upon path to Gaius.
正如他们把伊莉西娅带走
As their will has removed Ilithyia from it.
你疯了吗
Have you lost mind?
这是你哥哥的 对吧
It's your brother's, is it not?
你怎么拿到的
How did you come by this?
藏在阿舒尔的财物当中
Hidden amongst Ashur's treasures.
不过这个坏家伙只听命于
Yet the villain moves only upon command
盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博
of Gaius Claudius Glaber.
葛雷博答应这些条件了吗
Glaber agrees to terms.
我要去阿泰拉 完成这笔交易
I am for Atella, see it done.
但他选择向我复仇 而不是救你
He chose vengeance against me, over your life.
你放我走
You let me live?
别以为我是好心
Do not think it a kindness.
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《怪物》
卢戈
Lugo!
睁开你的狗眼
Open fucking eyes.
出什么事了吗
To see what?
小家伙 别草木皆兵
Wake when trees attack, little man.
是罗马军队
Romans!
操蛋的罗马人来了
Fucking Romans!
快点
Move!
够了
Enough!
都住手
Stand down!
你这是在搞演习
This was but fucking test?
要不是的话
If it had not been…
你们现在都没命了
you would all be for the afterlife.
下次再也不会这样措手不及了
We will not be taken unaware next time.
我希望大家说到做到
I would see words forged into action.
都起来 吃早饭
Rise and take morning meal.
今天要干的事多着呢
The day ahead of us will be long.
我早上起来
It causes worry
发现你不在身边 很是担心
to stir and find you gone from our bed.
我睡不着
I could not remain there.
老想着那些过早离开我们的可怜人
The mind churns with thoughts of those taken too soon from us.
还有那些夺走他们性命的畜生
And the monsters who tore them from loving embrace.
我们失去的都很多
We have both suffered immeasurable loss.
只能在彼此的身上
We must take comforts from what we have found…
寻找安慰
in each other…
我太冒失了 很后悔
I have moved foolishly, and with regret.
导致你没有机会悼念妻子
That I have denied you opportunity to properly mourn your wife.
她只是一段回忆
She is but fleeting memory…
如夜晚的迷雾
one that shall fade
在清晨阳光的照耀下
as the night mist,
转瞬间便无影无踪
caressed by morning sun…
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia…?
孩子怎么样
What of the child?
她肚子里有动静
It yet moves within her.
她醒了
She wakes.
出去
Out.
你是真的存在吗
Are you of this world?
握着我的手
Take hand,
你就知道我是真实的
and know that I am flesh.
都退下
Leave us.
我还以为你已经不在人世了
I thought you gone from this world.
我也这么想过
As did I.
不过诸神慈悲 让我又回到你的身边
Yet the gods have seen me returned to your arms.
真是福气
It is a blessing.
我们的孩子也有福
One shared by our child.
我体内的小生命
The warmth of the life inside me…
在我最绝望的时候给予我力量和安慰
it gave strength and comfort, when all seemed lost.
你怎么逃出来的
How did you escape?
不是逃出来的
I could not.
他放了我
He let me go.
斯巴达克斯放了你
Spartacus released you?
他说
He said…
就算杀了我也毫无意义
that taking my life would have no meaning.
你被关在哪儿
And where were you held?
我不知道
I do not know.
我双手被绑 眼睛也被蒙上
I was bound and stripped of sight.
甘尼克斯怎么把你带到那儿的
How did Gannicus carry you to him?
骑了半天马
By horse for part of a day.
又在林子里走了很久
By foot through woods for hours more.
你没看到他们的藏身之地吗
And you saw nothing of their camp?
只见过关我的那个潮湿的洞
Only the dank hole they kept me.
是在地下的
Dug into the earth?
还是用石头和木头搭起来的
Or made of stone and wood?
这又有什么关系
What does it fucking matter?
是石头砌成的
It was made of stone,
还有木头柱子
with beams of wood.
石头上还刻了很多乱糟糟的字
Scribblings carved into the rock.
上面说些什么
What did they say?
我不知道
I did not know.
字迹不全 而且很模糊
They were faded and broken.
用什么语言写的
In what tongue were they etched?
看着像希腊语
They appeared Greek.
为什么我不在我们的卧室里
Why am I not in our bedchambers?
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia
我还以为是在做梦
I thought it a dream.
你抱着赛皮娅
Seppia in your arms…
上下其手
Your hands upon her…
斯巴达克斯说的对
Spartacus was right.
就算我死了也没有什么意义
My death would not have held meaning.
你已经不爱我了
You do not love me.
你觉得出乎意料吗
And you greet this as revelation?
你一次又一次地伤我的心
Time and again you tore my heart from my chest.
我心里没有你了 这很奇怪吗
Is it a wonder it now stands empty in your regard?
我们之间什么都没有了吗
Is there nothing left between us?
我曾经这么问过你
I once asked the same of you.
还记得你是怎么回答的吗
Do you recall your reply?
我受的罪还不够吗
Have I not suffered enough for it?
我想回到从前的生活
I would have life as it was,
让我的丈夫陪在身边
with my husband beside me.
你所说的人已经不在了
The man you speak of no longer exists.
那我面前的你又是谁
Then what stands before me?
一头怪物
A monster.
灾难创造我的躯体
Rough hewn by unfortunate events,
绝境给了我生命
and given breath by necessity.
如果我们这么争吵不休
We cannot defend the temple
就不可能守住这座神庙
if we are at odds with one another.
派个能打的跟卢戈站岗
Give Lugo warrior to share watch!
不要这种个子小 卵蛋也小的
Not little man, with little balls!
我的卵蛋也没有失职
My balls did not allow breach.
你当时眼睛闭上了 做美梦了吧
Your eyes were closed in pursuit of dreams.
你睡着了
You fell to slumber?
你还怪罪纳西尔 你个懒猪
And you blame Nasir, you lazy shit?
别顾着维护你家的小男孩了
Turn effort from defending your boy,
好好检讨你自个儿的问题吧
and look upon your own failings.
那我们就再来一次
Then Let us relive the moment,
看我怎么弄死你
and see different fucking result.
罗马人快来了
The Romans will come.
如果他们发现我们起内讧
And if they find us divided,
我们必败无疑
we will fall before them.
说点有用的
Words of meaning.
她说的对
She speaks the truth.
你想让我们怎么样
What would you have us do?
保护好你那个猪头别挨打
Try not to get your fucking head bashed.
脸皮真厚
Bold words,
自个儿倒地的速度那么快
for one who tumbled so quickly.
那是因为我手里没家伙
I was absent fucking sword!
为啥这小家伙有剑 卢戈却没有
Why does little man have sword, and not Lugo?
我们总不能用他妈的木棍戳罗马人吧
We cannot face the Romans with fucking sticks.
那我就教你用弓箭
Then I will teach you the bow
臭婊子会耍弓了不起吗
我们是莱茵河东岸的汉子
We are from east of the Rhine.
我们他妈的只玩剑
We fight with fucking steel.
我们有什么就用什么
We must use what we have.
为啥你要放了那罗马婊子
人家什么都没给
她问你为何葛雷博没按要求
She asks why you let Ilithyia go,
给我们武器 你还要放伊莉西娅走
when Glaber did not trade weapons as promised.
这事儿我也想问
A thing I have also wondered.
杀了她 我们也达不到目的
Taking her life would not have gained us what we need.
这样的复仇是不正当的
It would only have served misplaced vengeance.
我们不是这样的人
We are better than this.
我们不像罗马人那样无耻
We are better than the Romans.
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus.
组织人员部署岗哨
See everyone to guarded position.
我们来进行日间突袭的演习
We will train against assault by light of day, …
还要提升我们夜间防御的能力
and attempt to elevate night's low defeat.
那就快开始吧
Let us see it done.
我不需要你帮忙
I have no need of aid.
卢戈 纳西尔
Lugo! Nasir!
去墙上站岗
Take position upon wall.
多纳 纳美特斯人
Donar! Nemetes!
莱顿 萨克莎
Lydon! Saxa!
跟我来
Fall to my side!
恐怕白天的结果也是一样
I fear result will be the same in light of day.
我们太不团结了
We are not a fist,
根本就是一盘散沙
but fingers twitching absent single purpose.
他们听到了我的话
My words crash upon ear,
可是心里无法接受
but fail to pierce heart.
那就用猛药治
Then we must stab deeper.
不然我们惩罚一下
Perhaps a punishment, for those
训练中表现不好的人
who fail in the day's training?
我们不能像罗马人那样
You cannot forge trust and loyalty
相信鞭子可以抽出信任和忠诚
at the ends of a whip, as the Romans believe.
那该怎么办啊
Then what would you use?
香吻一枚 甜言蜜语
Soft kisses and whispers of love?
叫上伏尔柯和哈鲁德斯
Gather Fulco and Harudes.
我要你们办件事
There is a thing I would have you do.
你想干嘛
What are your thoughts?
把这盘散沙捏成一团
To see fingers joined in single purpose.
这件事太令人遗憾了
It is a thing of much regret.
卢修斯永远离开了我们
Lucius is no longer among us.
心里好难受
A loss keenly felt.
但我们必须尽快振作起来
Yet we must move from wounded heart.
还有很多事情要做
Turn towards what must be done.
我要你训练更多的弓箭手
I would have you train more archers,
就按你的建议
as you suggested.
你只需要我做这些吗
Is that all you woul have from me?
拿上你的弓
Gather your bow.
你不来跟我睡了
You have not slept by my side.
除了命令 就没讲过别的话
You do not speak, unless to give order.
你还要惩罚我多久啊
How long do you seek to punish me?
我不是这意思
It's not my intent.
可是结果都一样
Yet result stands the same.
你抛弃了我
You turn from me.
是你抛弃自己
You turned from yourself,
在你打算杀伊莉西娅的时候
when you made attempt upon Ilithyia.
这种行为导致你一辈子都有污点
An act that would have stained you forever.
我只希望你能够清清白白
I thought only to save you from the same.
你是想保住我们曾经的感情
You thought to save what we had.
曾经
Had?
你在我怀里寻求不到安慰了吗
Can you no longer find comfort in my arms?
那你在我怀里呢
Can you find such in mine?
有
Yes.
只要你愿意多付出一点真心
If you would but give me more of your heart.
能给的我全都给你了
I have given all that remains.
这还不够
It this not enough.
对
No.
是不够
It is not.
我们去训练吧
Let us see to training.
还有很多事要做
And what must be done.
他不爱你
He does not love you…
你放我走
You let me live…
别以为我是好心
Do not think it a kindness…
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia?
诸神一定听到了我的祈祷
The gods have heard my prayers.
才把你送回我的怀抱
To return you to my arms…
只有你给我这么热烈的拥抱
You alone offer such embrace.
自从你离开了我
I have not taken food nor rest
我整天寝食难安
since you were torn from them.
没有你
Nor would I have,
我宁愿追随你而去
until I had followed you to suspected fate.
你对我真是太贴心了
Would that all held me as close to heart.
正因为你 我还活着
Well, you're the reason that mine still beats.
你和你神赐的祝福
You and the blessing you carry.
我以前从来没这样想过
I have never considered it as such.
但是到了最后的时刻
Yet in that final moment,
当我以为自己马上要死了
when I thought life was forfeit,
我觉得好悲伤
I felt a great sadness.
不是为我自己 而是为了我无辜的孩子
Not for myself, but for innocent child,
他在为母亲犯的错误而受罚
doomed to suffer for the mistakes of the mother.
我们都犯过很多错
We have both made many.
这孩子是斯巴达克斯的
The child is Spartacus'.
你骗我跟他上床的那天晚上
He gave seed the night you maneuvered me
他给我的
into laying with him.
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia
我已经不怪你了
I no longer lay blame at your feet.
是我逼你报复的
It was my hands that forced you to seek vengeance.
我无所依靠是自找的
My choices that have cast me adrift.
与我恨过的女人相偎相依
Clinging to a woman I once hated.
还有了一个我不该爱却又爱上的孩子
And a child I unreasonably grow to love.
感受在你心中盛开的希望和喜悦吧
To feel such hope and such joy blossoming within you…
那是世上最珍贵的花
That's the rarest of all flowers.
无所谓花儿盛开的原因
Regardless of why it blooms.
抱歉
Apologies.
我不知道你其实…
I-I did not know you were ah
抱歉
Apologies.
她想取代我在盖尤斯身边的地位
She moves to assume my place at Gaius' side.
总有一天她会发现他的真面目
One day she will see him for what he truly is.
噢 她已经发现了
Oh, her eyes have already been opened.
赛普修斯不是被他的奴隶杀死的
Seppius was not murdered by his slaves,
凶手是你丈夫
but by your husband.
盖尤斯
Gaius?
我在一件非常不幸的事情当中
A thing which I discovered through most
发现了此事 然后只告诉了赛皮娅
unfortunate manner, and shared only with Seppia.
那她还留在这里干嘛
Yet she stays within this house?
还要把身体献给仇人玩弄吗
Body offered to the man that so wounded her?
现在离开只会引起怀疑
To leave now would only serve to arouse suspicion.
但她心里已经燃起了复仇之火
Yet she burns with thoughts of avenging her brother.
我要让那把火烧起来
I would see such embers given breath.
等到烈火燃尽
And in resulting flames,
我和我的孩子
my child and I
就能凤凰涅槃 浴火重生了
to rise from the ashes of ill-fated past.
他们骑马前行
They traveled by horse,
然后花了几个钟头步行穿过森林
then on foot through forest for several hours.
但她并不知道走的方向
Yet she does not know what direction she travelled in.
斯巴达克斯攻击过卢卡尼亚矿区
Spartacus has attacked the mine of Lucania here…
卡普亚的竞技场
The arena in Capua…
那不勒斯的港口
The port of Neapolis…
还企图在阿泰拉进行交易
And attempted to make trade in Atella…
路线显示出他们从里到外的活动范围
The curve would suggest they move outward from a central position,
就在这一片
in this region.
还是太大了
Yet a vast area.
她还说了什么有用的情报吗
Did she mention anything more that may be of use?
只说她被关在地下
Only that she was kept beneath ground.
那间屋子的墙上有模糊的字母
In a chamber with faded lettering,
也许是希腊文
perhaps Greek in origin.
请稍等
Apologies…
是罗马人 卢修斯•凯利乌斯
He's Roman, Lucius Caelius.
去喝点酒 吃点东西吧
See yourself to wine and food.
他的努力有成果了
His efforts bear fruit?
还是从斯巴达克斯自家后院摘的果子呢
Plucked from Spartacus' own garden.
他的忘年交名叫卢修斯•凯利乌斯
His overly ripe friend goes by name of Lucius Caelius.
打探后得知 他是那不勒斯和阿泰拉
Known by those questioned to frequent market
两地集市的常客
in Neapolis and Atella…
他住在维苏威的背面
and to dwell in the shadows of Vesuvius.
范围还是太大
Still too vast an area.
您夫人敏锐的眼光缩小了范围
Made smaller by your wife's discerning eyes.
山脚下有一座废弃多年的神庙
There is a, a temple near mountain's foot, long abandoned.
是由希腊人建造的
Erected many years past by Greek hands.
我们可以夜里行军
Then we march at nightfall,
黎明时分就能抓到斯巴达克斯了
and by dawn's light see an end to Spartacus.
我建议一定要小心谨慎
I would urge no small amount of caution.
据我所知 这座庙有一堵围墙
If memory serve, there's a wall protecting this temple.
斯巴达克斯一伙人
Spartacus and his men will surely
肯定加强了防御
have fortified position.
那我们就要展现罗马军队的强大实力
Then we shall bring to bear the fiery might of Rome
打破他们的防线
and see defenses fall,
再干掉那个不自量力的家伙
in advance of the man himself.
集结你的人手
Prepare your men.
等到那个荣耀的时刻
And I would have you at my side,
我要你共同感受
to share in glorious moment.
不胜荣幸
A great honor.
这会子再要求别的实在有愧
It shames me to seek reward beyond it,
可我实在太想 不由自主地犯了傻
yet heart's desire turns reason a fool.
你有很多面 叙利亚人
You are many things, Syrian.
但我可不会相信你傻
But do not expect me to believe you a fool.
想要什么就说
Give voice to your desire.
我自会考虑
See it considered.
纳美特斯人
Nemetes!
还没发令你就进攻了
You attack before command is given!
在罗马人靠近之前 你要隐蔽好
You must remain hidden until the Romans are drawn in.
你就任凭他们突破进来
You would see them breach the wall?
我们是要困住他们 傻帽
We would see them trapped, you simple fuck.
就像瓮中之鳖
Like fish in a net.
有辆马车过来了
A wagon approaches.
艾力冈领头呢
Agron leads it.
他又不听命令打劫马车了
He has attacked another one, without command.
不是
No.
是我让他去的
He acts upon my orders.
去干什么
Towards what purpose?
搞来我们目前最需要的东西
To secure what we desperately need.
要不是那紧锁的眉头 我都不认识他了
I barely know the man, absent furrowed brow.
他可不是酒鬼
He is not a man of drunken pursuits.
看眉毛可能看不出来
His brow may not reveal it,
不过他心里肯定有什么想法
but there is yet intent upon mind.
听到大家的欢声笑语 我很开心
It lifts heart, to hear voices raised in spirit.
我们这么团结
To see us bonded.
不管有无烙印
Not by brand.
不因故乡有别
Not by homeland.
只因共同的理想
But by an ideal.
每个人 不论男女
That every man…every woman…
不论降临人世 生存还是死亡
should be born, should live, and should die
都应该品尝到自由的滋味
with the taste of freedom forever upon their lips.
但是 我们要尽弃前嫌
Yet if we are to defeat the Romans,
团结一心
we must put aside our differeces,
才能击溃罗马人
and come together as one.
我们来一场比赛吧
Let us have sport!
彼此看不顺眼的人组成一组
Pairing those of you with ill feelings
与对手切磋切磋
against your equals.
试看对胜利的渴望
And let us see if thirst for victory
能否战胜小小的嫌隙
triumphs petty quarrel.
他的想法出来了
Intent is revealed.
多纳
Donar!
纳美特斯人
Nemetes!
就位
Take position.
卢戈
Lugo!
纳西尔
Nasir!
你们和他们对战
You will face them.
我们会赢的
We'll win.
只要你别碍事 小家伙
If you keep out of way, little man.
你他妈的别这么叫我
Don't fucking call me that.
开始
Begin!
多么美好的事情啊 不是吗
It is a thing of beauty, is it not?
一个人只要努力奋斗
What a man may accomplish
能实现多大的成就啊
if mind is set to purpose.
不过还缺一样东西
Yet there something missing…
自由
freedom
能够无拘无束地挥霍财宝
To see treasures put to use absent constraint.
能够独立自主地作出决定
To live, knowing each choice made
这才是人生
is your own.
斯巴达克斯在这点上和我想法一样
Spartacus and I stand together in such desires.
你也就是一个低贱的奴隶
Then you find yourself in low company.
情况很快就会变了
Soon to be elevated.
阿舒尔做到了不可能做到的事
Ashur has done the impossible,
发现了那个大坏蛋的藏身之处
and discovered where the dreaded villain secrets himself.
作为回报
And in reward,
葛雷博给我许了好东西呢
Glaber bestows deepest wish upon me.
他赐予你自由
He sets you free?
等在维苏威拿下斯巴达克斯后
After we take Spartacus at Vesuvius.
恢复自由身不过是开胃菜
Yet releasing me from bond is but a taste
美味佳肴还多着呢
of more sumptuous meal.
你就一个人慢慢享用吧
One which you shall feast upon alone.
等打败了斯巴达克斯
After Spartacus is defeated,
伊莉西娅就跟她丈夫回罗马
Ilithyia will return to Rome with her husband.
我是她的密友 自然随她同行
And trusted friend will be at her side.
恐怕伊莉西娅要另找密友了
I fear Ilithyia must find a new one.
你要留下来
You will remain here.
继续扮演爱妻的角色
To assume mantle of loving wife.
葛雷博不会同意的
Glaber will not allow this.
他不光同意了
He more than allows it.
还另有赏赐
He gives union blessing.
把这座训练场送给我
And presents gift of this ludus
以表彰我出色的贡献
in recognition of honored service.
他竟然将我丈夫的遗产赠予你
He gives you my husband's legacy?
亲爱的 我们结成夫妻后
We shall forge a new one, my love.
可以建立新的家业
As husband and wife.
然后共同见证阿舒尔家族的辉煌崛起
And together we shall see the noble rise of the House of Ashur.
要士兵整顿装备 做好黎明前行军的准备
Have the men equipped and ready to travel by sunrise.
你负责这件事
See that it happens.
有没有拿到我们要的东西
You were able to acquire what is needed?
正在从那不勒斯过来的路上
They are upon road from Neapolis.
你去迎接 催促他们尽快抵达
Meet them and hasten arrival.
我要马不停蹄地赶往南方
I will hold no delay in marching south.
我建议你换条路线
I would advise a different course.
我来此传达元老院的指示
I've been dispatched with message from the Senate.
你要停止对斯巴达克斯的追捕
You are to cease pursuit of Spartacus
并即刻返回罗马
and return to Rome immediately.
我是罗马共和国的民政官
I am a praetor of the Republic.
元老院无权对我做出这样的要求
The Senate holds no power to make such demands of me.
没错 他们无权
True, they do not.
他们只能建议你采取某种行动
They have only the power to recommend a path of action.
不打算晋升的人
One only a man with no intent to rise above
大可以选择无视
current position would ignore.
他们竟然派一个意图夺我妻子的人来传话
And they send words through the man who conspires to claim my wife?
有此想法的不止我一个 对吗
I am hardly alone in such ambitions, am I?
我偶然听到谣言
Troubling news has lit upon ear.
说我没得到的女人 让斯巴达克斯带走了
That Spartacus has seized what I could not.
你简直不知所谓
You do not know of what you speak.
你简直愚不可及
And you are an incompetent fool,
竟然让一个奴隶劫走了你老婆
to allow your wife to be taken by a slave.
劫走
Taken?
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia?
你的消息似乎不可靠啊
It appears you have been misinformed.
我不过是到床上休息去了
I have been taken only to bed,
怀孕期快结束了
my child causing unexpected discomfort
孩子有点不安分
in waning months of pregnancy.
你脸上的瘀伤也是孩子造成的
Did it also cause the bruise upon your cheek?
不 不是
No, it did not.
是我不小心
The fault was mine.
沐浴后不经意跌倒 就摔伤了
A misplaced step as I was coming from the bath.
那你走路要更小心才是
You should choose footing more carefully.
你说话也要小心
As you should choose your words.
回家去吧 盖尤斯
Return home, Gaius.
看紧你妻子
And tend to your wife,
当心又让人家给抢走了
before yet another man makes attempt upon her.
斯巴达克斯伏法之日 就是我荣归之时
I shall take my leave when Spartacus falls.
你已经拖得太久了
A task long overdue in its completion.
如今尽在我掌握
Yet now within grasp.
我率军到维苏威 他的末日就到了
I march to Vesuvius, and an end to the man.
维苏威
Vesuvius?
他就躲在那里吗
Is that where he hides?
此事不劳你费心
It is of no concern to you.
元老院另有决定
The Senate believes otherwise.
由我率领称职的军队 接过你的任务
I've been appointed to assume your place with an army of worth,
将斯巴达克斯绳之于法
and bring Spartacus to justice.
如果我拒绝妥协呢
And if I refuse to step aside?
那是你自己的选择
It is a choice you are free to make.
不过你要再想从这堆烂摊子里爬起来
But one that would end all hope of rising from the shit
就是痴心妄想了
you have mired yourself in.
保住你那点仅剩的名誉
Save what little worth your name yet holds,
回罗马去吧
and set path towards Rome.
瓦里留斯
Varinius!
感谢诸神 你收到了我的信
Thank the gods you received my message.
结果我一过来
And I respond to it,
却发现伊莉西娅好端端地坐在家里
only to find Ilithyia safely within these walls.
斯巴达克斯放了她
Spartacus freed her.
他为什么对敌人的妻子大发慈悲
Why would he show mercy to the wife of the man that hunts him?
我才不会花时间猜度一个奴隶的想法呢
I make no attempt to understand the mind of a slave.
你的时间都用来编造绑架的谣言了
Your time instead spent inventing tales of abduction.
你哥哥的事不会也是编的吧
Does what you write of your brother hold similar merit?
我告诉你的都是真的
Everything I have told you is true.
盖尤斯杀了我哥哥
Gaius took the life of my brother.
那你有什么证据
And what evidence do you claim,
竟敢指控一位罗马民政官
to dare place charge against a praetor of Rome?
赛普修斯的手镯 跟我的一样
Seppius' bracelet, a mirror of my own.
藏在一个家伙的财物里 他绝对服从…
Found hidden among the belongings of a man loyal to
就一个破手镯顶屁用
A fucking bracelet is all you hold?
你个傻丫头
You stupid little girl.
你千万不要一走了之
Please do not turn from this.
盖尤斯必须为他的行为付出代价
Gaius must pay for what he's done.
我不喜欢那家伙
I hold no love for the man.
不过这种空穴来风的指控
Yet to make accusation based upon the air
你哭红了眼睛也没有用
and teary eye would serve no purpose.
多说无益
Nor will further words.
你发动攻击之前放松了防守
You lower guard just before launching attack.
现在说太晚了
Advice gained too late.
我们输了
We lose.
不过这小家伙打起来很威猛
But little man fight like giant!
喝酒和比赛
Drink and contest.
这办法很聪明 是该让大家团结起来
A clever strategy, to forge necessary bonds.
好事还在后面呢
And I would see more follow.
打得非常漂亮
A battle well fought.
再来一组较量吧
Let us have new contest!
艾力冈
Agron!
克雷斯
Crixus!
搞定他 艾力冈
Get him Agron!
艾力冈 你打不着他
He's too fast for you Agron!
就位
Take position.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus!
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus!
是他们的对手
Stand against them.
打败他们很容易
We can easily best them.
只要我们齐心协力
If we fight as one.
拿着 混球
Hold this, you fuck!
不准喝
Do not drink it.
去吧 做你该做的事
Come and do what is necessary.
准备
Ready!
开始
Begin!
上啊 克雷斯
Come on, Crixus!
告诉他谁才是真正的冠军 克雷斯
Teach him who the true champion is, Crixus!
真让人惊讶 你的变化好大
It astounds to witness the change in you.
只要有爱 没有什么是不可能的
The world itself can reverse course, if moved by loving hands.
你好幸福
A blessing.
你们俩这么珍惜对方
To hold each other in such regard.
斯巴达克斯对你也一样
As Spartacus holds you.
那是以前
No longer.
艾力冈
Agron.
打得漂亮
You fought well.
作为一个来自莱茵河东岸的混球
For a simple fuck from east of the Rhine.
你也不错
As did you.
作为一个吃屎的高卢人
For a shit-eating Gaul.
既然吃了败仗 我们去喝杯酒解解愁吧
Let us share drink, and balm wounded pride.
失去亲人确实很难受
To suffer the sting of loss.
过去的事情已经没办法改变了
Absent course to right what has been done.
我照你的建议 给瓦里留斯写了信
I sent for Varinius, as you prompted.
结果他既不理我 更不碰我
Only to have him shun word and touch.
你不是纯洁无暇的小姑娘了
You are no longer a girl, unblemished by the world.
你现在是个女人
You're a woman now.
当男人们兴奋得发抖时
And our hands shape the fates,
命运就掌握在我们手中了
when those of men tremble.
发抖的是我
It is I who tremble.
一想到盖尤斯摸我就发抖
The thought of Gaius' hands upon me.
好了 好了
There, there.
正因为如此 才有动手的机会呀
It is such desire that presents opportunity.
这种事情我做不到
You suggest the impossible.
那你就想想以后的日子怎么过吧
I suggest only that you consider the years unfolding before you.
盖尤斯•克劳迪斯•葛雷博在罗马
Every moment swollen with the knowledge
舒舒服服地生活
that Gaius Claudius Glaber
而你只能眼睁睁地度日如年
lives out his life in the privileged lap of Rome.
你的哥哥则死不瞑目
While your brother is forever denied breath.
不应该这样
It should not be so.
是不应该
It should not.
我所珍惜的一切也被夺走了
Everything I held dear was taken from me as well.
这个宅子
This house.
我的丈夫
My husband.
养儿育女的期望
Promise of a child…
他们犯下的罪孽岂能不了了之
The things that have been done to us cannot stand unanswered.
如果听之任之
To allow it would be to turn
我们怎么对得起死去的亲人
from those we claimed to have loved.
就没有别的方法了吗
Is there no other course?
如果你希望为哥哥的死报仇
If you wish to see your brother's murder avenged…
那就必须见血
blood must be spilled.
你说服她了吗
She is moved towards deed?
应该没问题
I believe it so.
你真的是这样想的吗
You are certain this is what you desire?
既然言语打动不了盖尤斯
If Gaius is not moved by pleading word,
那我就选择鲜血和死亡
then I will have blood and death.
等到办成了这件事
And in the bringing of it,
生活就恢复原样了
my life returned to me.
是真的吗
Is it true?
听说你要去罗马了
That you depart for Rome?
我别无选择
I'm left with little choice.
就这么走了
It is a terrible thing
真是太糟糕了
to be stripped of such.
那家伙给我造成的伤害不止如此
Made more grievous by hand that removes it.
你说瓦里留斯
You speak of Varinius?
他又打算夺走本应该属于我的东西
He once more makes attempt to claim what is rightfully mine.
正如斯巴达克斯夺走我哥哥的命
As Spartacus claimed my brother's life?
确实非常不幸
An unfortunate tragedy.
凶手还没有伏法
One that yet demands justice.
元老院把任务给了瓦里留斯
The Senate appoints Varinius the task.
我不相信他有能耐
I do not have faith in him,
干掉那个活该千刀万剐的家伙
to take the life of the man responsible for grievous injury.
我也不信
Nor I.
还是别想这些不愉快的事了
Yet we must turn from such thought,
不如在温暖的怀抱里寻找慰藉吧
and seek comfort in the hands of warm embrace
就是你夺走了我哥哥的命
Your fucking hands ripped my brother from this world.
我要你血债血偿
And mine shall see you from it.
盖尤斯
Gaius…
我不要你
I cast you aside…
你却救我的命
yet you save my life?
你是我的夫君
You are my husband.
我们回不去了
We cannot be what we were.
那就不必回去了
Then let us be what we are.
我们都狠狠地伤害过对方
We have done terrible things to each other.
如今我要调转矛头
I would see such venom turned outward
对付真正的敌人
to those truly deserving of it.
赛皮娅
Seppia.
元老院
The Senate.
还有他们派来抢夺你荣誉的人
And the man they dispatch to steal your glory.
你要对付瓦里留斯
You would move against Varinius?
我们都是怪物 盖尤斯
We are both monsters, Gaius.
我们联起手来
Let us be so together,
搅个天翻地覆
and seize the fucking heavens.
我要去攻打维苏威了
I shall march to Vesuvius.
完成心愿
See it done.
稍等片刻又如何
Pause but a moment.
你已经太久没有上我了
I have been too long absent you inside me.
原谅我
Forgive me.
我一时间失控了
I lose myself in the moment.
不
No.
一直以来是我失控了
It is I who have been lost.
是你的爱抚 指引我回家
And your touch that guides me home…
*剑举高*
*And lift your sword*
*酒喝饱*
*Drain your wine*
*尿一泡*
*Drain your cock*
*良宵苦短 黎明快到*
*Dawn comes too soon night flees too soon*
*杯莫停 喝到高*
*So lift fucking cup! Lift fucking cup…*
我还是认为你会带我们早早送死
I still believe you will see us all to untimely end.
不过这种死法真他妈的痛快
Yet it will be a glorious fucking death.
有信号
The signal.
葛雷博
Glaber.
葛雷博躲在后面指挥
Glaber commands from the rear.
懦夫的做派
A coward's position.
他的军队阵型非常紧密
He will advance his troops in tight formation,
实行压倒性打击
intending to overpower.
这是罗马人的方式
It is the Roman way.
让他们见识一下我们的方式
We will teach them ours.
退回神庙
Fall back to the temple!
伏尔柯
Fulco!
人太多了
There are too many!
撤
Move!
民政官大人
Praetor!
叛军撤退了
The rebels are in retreat
一排
Phase one.
二排
Two.
三排
Three.
冲
Let's march!
你不是我要找的人
You are not the man I seek.
放下武器
Lay down your arms!
照做
Do it!
这下我们有兵器了
Now we have steel.
好啊
Yeah!
把他们的武器都拿过来
Gather their weapons.
好啊
Yeah!
瓦里留斯
Varinius.
你还欠我一笔血债 艾克和莱斯克斯
I owe you a debt of blood, for Acer and Rhaskos.
等他坦白交代了 再报仇不迟
And we shall see it paid, after answer is given.
葛雷博呢
Where is Glaber?
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus
拉
Pull!
点火
Ignite!
推
Push!
准备
On the ready!
Ready!
听我号令
On my signal!
填
Load!
点火
Ignite!
放
Release!
再来
Again!
我们必须撤走
We have to move!
撤退
Fall back!
进地道
Into the tunnel!
走 走 快走
Go! Go! Go! Go!
克雷斯
Crixus
走
Go!
我们马上来
We'll follow!
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus!
快走
Move!
走 快走
Move! Move!
艾力冈
Agron!
走
Move!
走 跟上
Go! Come on!
快
Quickly!
走
Move!
不要停
Keep moving!
他们人太多
There are too many of them.
走山路
The mountain path!
快
Hurry!
没有别的路了
There is no other path now.
我们被包围了
We'll be trapped
没办法了
There's no choice!
我们必须走
We must move!
走
Go!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
走
Go!
Move!
这边
This way!
还有别的路上山吗
Is there no other way to gain the mountain?
没有 除了他们用来逃命的那条小道
None, save for the narrow path they escaped upon.
我们在追击时损失了不少人
Scores of men were lost, in attempted pursuit.
垂死挣扎
Foolish endeavor.
如今他们居高临下
They now hold the high ground.
占尽优势
We've lost advantage.
你打算放过他们吗
You would let them go free?
不
No.
我要让他们拿泥巴和石头开庆功宴
I would let them feast on mud and rock.
等他们饿得发狂 从上面跑下来时
And when hunger and madness drive them from their perch…
再把他们赶尽杀绝
We shall kill them all.